<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Anja Giudici</title>
    <link>https://anjagiudici.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://anjagiudici.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://anjagiudici.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://anjagiudici.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Education against (liberal) democracy</title>
      <link>https://anjagiudici.github.io/project/eduvsdemo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://anjagiudici.github.io/project/eduvsdemo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This ongoing project is financed by the Swiss National Science Foundation (grant nr. 184086, 2019-2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education and politics are closely connected. Education is always directed at, and constituted by, specific societal and political purposes. Vice-versa, every societal and political project needs to con- sider how to mould the individuals and the society that will sustain it. After World War II, a broad consensus emerged in the Western world that education and schooling should serve to consolidate liberal democracy. Education reforms in this period aimed to mitigate societal inequality, prevent children from developing illiberal and authoritarian attitudes, and teach them the benefits and morality of political participation. However, liberal democracy as a political ideal is being increasingly contested – especially by representatives of the far right-wing of the political spectrum. In the last few decades, far-right parties and intellectuals have moved from fringe status to mainstream players in electoral politics and the societal debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The far right’s visions of society and politics are fundamentally at odds with liberal-democratic fundamental values such as pluralism, equality, and individual rights, which have underpinned educational thinking and policy since 1945. Does that therefore mean the education systems the movement envisions is also fundamentally different from what we have seen so far? If education is to be conceived of as the “twin-sister of democratic theory” (Honneth, 2012) how do the twin-sisters of undemocratic postwar-fascism and populist-nativist-authoritarianism look? Do they have a specific look at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project represents the first empirically-based analysis of the educational of the western European postwar far right’s educational ideas and politics. Its focus is twofold. First, it investigates how this movement wants to see formal education governed and structured, as well as what content it believes education should convey. Second, it studies how the movement has engaged in educational politics, thus identifying strategic and organisational choices in this particular policy field. The project involves multi-archive research, and analysis of programmatic documents produced by what are deemed the most influential organisations of the western European postwar radical right from the 1950s to the 2000s. This includes parties and think tanks in France, Germany, Italy, and the U.K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project will provide a novel interdisciplinary theoretical contribution to education, as well as to political science and history. On the one hand, it complements it complements social scientists’ understanding on the ideology and strategies of the postwar radical right. On the other hand, it yields new insights into the relationship between political and educational ideals, allowing us to reflect on what actually characterises education in liberal and democratic terms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Education &amp; interwar fascisms</title>
      <link>https://anjagiudici.github.io/project/fascism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://anjagiudici.github.io/project/fascism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last few years, several studies have disclosed similarities between different interwar fascist regimes and movements across Europe. The literature also shows how these regimes&amp;rsquo; and movements&amp;rsquo; mutual relationships and exchanges shaped their ideology and practices. Fascist movements all over Europe founded their political preferences and policies on the principles of the (racial) superiority of the native monistically conceived Volksgemeinschaft, as well as a preference for authoritarianism and a strong leadership over liberal democracy. In this contexts, educational institutions, from the family, to youth organisations, to schooling, were considered crucial, as they provided a theatre in which of a strong, healthy national community could be moulded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this ongoing project, colleagues and I aim to integrate this novel conception of pre- and interwar fascism into the study of the history and politics of education.
The project has brought together scholars interested in the educational ideas and practices of authoritarian regimes and movements across Europe, focussing specifically on countries outside of the traditional – and well-studied – cradles of interwar fascism. Its results are documented in a number of articles that discuss the educational ideas, policy preferences, and politics of Swiss interwar fascism as well as a forthcoming special issue that brings together articles from different European areas. All these studies provide vivid demonstration how, the proliferation of fascism in the 1920s and 1930s stirred new dynamics in education circles across Europe and forced them to take a stance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Explaining Language Education Policy</title>
      <link>https://anjagiudici.github.io/project/languageedu/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://anjagiudici.github.io/project/languageedu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Language education policy matters. In fact, there is only one way to master a language: learn it. Despite often being couched in biological terms – mother tongue, language families, descent words –, language actually has little to do with nature. Languages are manmade, and while biology may provide individuals with the ability to acquire and use language, when it comes to particular languages, “[t]here are no genes; there is only learning”, as sociolinguist Einar Haugen (1973) puts it. As the prime institution for the professional conveyance of knowledge from one generation to the next, formal schooling plays a crucial role in enabling and regulating language learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everywhere, children enter schools with diverse sociolinguistic backgrounds. Therefore, decisions about the languages that are included in or excluded from school curricula have a major and differential impact how they experience schooling, as well as the degrees they will be able to acquire and the career paths they will be able to access. Since no society is monolingual, the choice of languages taught in formal schooling also carries implications on a societal level, affecting political entities’ overall economic success, and setting the premises for democratic deliberation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a series of studies, I have explored the patterns, development, as well as the determinants behind language education policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>(Educational) institutions dealing with societal diversity</title>
      <link>https://anjagiudici.github.io/project/diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://anjagiudici.github.io/project/diversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This series of studies and publications are the result of my collaborations with several political scientists, educationalists, and linguists. They explored how institutions of government and education deal with societal diversity, e.g. regarding language, culture, or gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
